Guide to the Doris Duke papers on the Shangri La residence, 1932-2003 and undated RL.01434
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Doris Duke papers on the Shangri La residence
1932-2003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke, Doris
RL.01434
16.8 Linear Feet
Traveling through many Muslim countries and parts of India during her honeymoon, Doris Duke was fascinated by Islamic cultural traditions, art and architecture. A visit to the Taj Mahal inspired Duke to eventually commission plans for the house she built in Hawaii. Duke engaged the architectural firm of Wyeth and King to design her Hawaiian home, and architects Marion Sims Wyeth and H. Drewry Baker worked closely with Duke to design the home, with Duke providing sketches and photographs of buildings and architectural details she had seen during her travels. Throughout her life, Doris Duke enthusiastically designed and redesigned her home and gardens, and in 1965 made a codicil in her will directing her executors to organize a foundation to manage and maintain Shangri La for the study and understanding of Middle Eastern art and culture. The collection tells the story of Shangri La, the most intimate of Doris Duke's residences. While the collection spans the years 1932 to 2003, the materials primarily begin in 1936, with correspondence relating to early discussions of architects to design Shangri La in what was then the U.S. Territory of Hawaii, and end in the mid to late 1990s with materials related to the handling of the Estate of Doris Duke after her death in 1993. The materials primarily detail the design, construction, decoration, and furnishing of Shangri La and the routine business matters of its daily operation.
approx. 10,680 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use. Due to the fragility of the Architectural records, The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Digital use copies in this collection have been migrated to a library server and can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access please contact Research Services prior to visiting the library.
Provenance
Materials in the Doris Duke papers on the Shangri La residence were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a donation from the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation in June 2009.
Historical Note
In 1935, when Doris Duke and her husband James Cromwell embarked on a honeymoon tour of the world, little did she know the trip would profoundly affect the rest of her life. Traveling through many Muslim countries and parts of India, she was fascinated by Islamic cultural traditions, art and architecture. A visit to the Taj Mahal inspired Duke to commission plans for a bedroom and bathroom suite in Florida but which eventually became the nucleus for the house she built in Hawaii. Duke engaged the architectural firm of Wyeth and King to design her Hawaiian home. Marion Sims Wyeth and supervising architect H. Drewry Baker worked closely with Duke to design the home, with Duke providing sketches and photographs of buildings and architectural details she had seen during her travels. Construction of the home began in early 1937 and the Cromwells moved into the main home in December of 1938. Completed at a cost of $1.4 million, the estate was at the time the most extensive residential project in the Territory of Hawaii. Furnishing the home was another major undertaking. Doris Duke and her husband traveled to Europe and the Middle East for four months in 1938 to acquire furnishings for their new home. Accompanied by Mary Crane, a graduate student at New York University, the purchases were deliberate and extensive and Duke was intimately involved in the decisions pertaining to their installation and display in the estate. Throughout her life, Doris Duke enthusiastically designed and redesigned her home and gardens, and in 1965 made a codicil in her will directing her executors to organize a foundation to manage and maintain Shangri La for the study and understanding of Middle Eastern art and culture.
Collection Overview
The Doris Duke papers on the Shangri La residence (formerly SL.2 and SL.2.8) are part of the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation Historical Archives which were donated to the Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library by the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation. The collection tells the story of Shangri La, the most intimate of Doris Duke's residences. While the collection spans the years 1932 to 2003, the materials primarily begin in 1936, with correspondence relating to early discussions of architects to design Shangri La in what was then the U.S. Territory of Hawaii, and end in the mid to late 1990s with materials related to the handling of the Estate of Doris Duke after her death in 1993. The collection is arranged into three series: Correspondence, Administrative Records, and Architectural Records. Nearly half of the correspondence specifically pertains to the design, construction, decoration, and furnishing of Shangri La. The remaining materials in the series detail the activities of Shangri La and include correspondence and memoranda documenting the routine business matters of its daily operation. The materials included in the Administrative Records series primarily document the expenses and daily operations of running and maintaining the Hawaiian residence. Included in this series are invoices and receipts for repairs and renovations to the residence, expenses and expenditures, and inventories of furniture, fixtures, and other household items. Also included in this series are weekly security reports, location diaries of Doris Duke's whereabouts, and recipes for a variety of meals that were presumably prepared at Shangri La. A majority of the architectural records in this collection are related to the design and construction of Shangri La. The materials in this collection are arranged loosely in chronological order.
Related Material
Duke Family Papers, 1885-1992
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Duke Family New York Apartments Collection, 1908-1997
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Architecture -- Designs and plans; Architectural drawing -- United States -- 20th century; Diamond Head (Hawaii); Islamic architecture; Islamic art; Cromwell, James H. R. (James Henry Roberts); Shangri La (Honolulu, Hawaii); Duke, Doris; Duke, Doris
- Correspondence, 1935-1993
  Scope and Contents note
  Primarily correspondence, but also includes telegrams, invoices, bills of lading, hand drawn designs and diagrams, hand written notes, and photographs.
  Nearly half of the correspondence is specifically related to the design, construction, decoration, and furnishing of Shangri La. While much of it is related to the business side of Shangri La, the personal side of life is also reflected as the authors often comment on current events and other daily activities. Correspondence includes Fredrick B. Bromfield's design of an Indian-inspired bedroom and bathroom for Doris Duke, letters outlining the monthly expenses for Marion Sims Wyeth's professional architectural services during the construction of the residence in Honolulu, letters and telegrams related to purchases of antique furniture, shipments of art and other household goods for Shangri La, and correspondence related to the Cromwell's five-week journey to Persia in 1938. Series also has extensive correspondence between James Cromwell and Moroccan designer Rene Martin, and antique dealers A. Rabenou of Tehran and Paris, and Asfar & Sarkis of Damascus all of which are related to the purchase of tiles, furniture and other pieces of art for Shangri La. Of particular interest is the correspondence of graduate student, Mary Crane, who became both an art adviser and friend to both Doris Duke and Marian Paschal. The typed and hand written letters, addressed to both Doris and Marian, often include hand drawn illustrations of items Crane either purchased for Doris or thought would be of interest. Materials also consist of letters and official documents related to the purchase and ultimate requisition by the War Shipping Administration of the Cromwell's yacht, the "Kailani LahiLahi"; correspondence exchanged between Johnny Gomez and S.L. (Stuart) Hawkins regarding administrative activities of Shangri La; quotes, billings, and invoices documenting the renovations and upkeep of the residence; and other miscellaneous letters, invoices and inventories related to the daily activities and routine business matters of Shangri La.
  Note: several letters from Rene Martin, A. Rabenou and Charles Asafar are written in French. While many of the letters include translation, there are some that do not.
  - Memoranda and lists of goods shipped from Calcutta, India by Thomas Cook & Son. 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence relating to the Cromwells’ work with F. B. Blomfield, architect hired to draw up plans for bedroom in Palm Beach, FL. Bedroom and adjoining rooms to be inspired by Taj Mahal. File also includes correspondence between Cromwells and Treanor & Fatio, architects. 1935–1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence relating to business activities concerning W.L. Baldwin, agent for the Cromwells, Wyeth & King, and other individuals responsible for certifying engineering agreements (Warren W. Chapin). 1936–1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, statements, etc. relating to damages to marble work. 1936–1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence relating to early discussions of architects to design Shangri La, shipments to HI., and day-to-day business affairs. File also includes financial ledger sheets noting payments to Wyeth & King from Doris Duke Cromwell, customs forms, and telegrams to Sam Kahanamoku from “Lahi Lahi.” 1936–1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence relating to business activities and shipments to Shangri La. Many of the letters are between William Dodsworth, Paris & JHRC and Rene Martin, Morocco, and JHRC concerning status of shipments and progress. 1937–1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence relating to the Cromwells’ purchase of Italian tile from Adolfo Loewi and furniture also from Loewi through Dodsworth, the Cromwells’ agent in Paris. 1937–1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence relating to purchases and shipments of Mr. JHRC and Doris Duke Cromwell through William Dodsworth, the Cromwells’ agent in Paris. 1937–1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence and related materials concerning Doris Duke’s boats, Kimo and Kailani Lahilahi in Hawaii, 1937–1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and related materials concerning a trip to Persia. 1938 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence relating to a variety of subject matters concerning Shangri La, architectural services by Wyeth & King, shipments to Shangri La. 1937-1938 (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence relating to a variety of subject matters concerning Shangri La, architectural services by Wyeth & King, shipments to Shangri La. 1937-1938 (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence relating to purchases and shipments from Asfar & Sarkis through William Dodsworth, the Cromwells’ agent in Paris. 1938 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence relating to purchases from Europe and the Middle East by Mr. JHRC and Doris Duke Cromwell. 1938–1939 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and related materials concerning transactions with Mr. Rabenou about tiles in Honolulu. 1938–1940 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence relating to purchases and shipments managed by Mary Crane in N.Y.C. and her updates to Doris Duke and Marian Paschal in Hawaii. Subjects include work by H. Kevorkian, work by J. Roshan, work by Louis Pursel, Hearst sale, repairs, and some casual conversations. File also includes pencil sketches by Wyeth & King, architects. 1938–1941, 1966–1967 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to business activities of James and Doris Duke Cromwell for Shangri La. File includes an exchange of correspondence between James Cromwell and Martin Munkacsi over ownership and sale of negatives created as part of spread in Life Magazine at Shangri La. 1939 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence relating to purchases and shipments from Asfar & Sarkis to Ruth Selwyn in N.Y. for Mr. and Mrs. JHR Cromwell. 1939 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence relating to a fountain produced by Asfar & Sarkis for the Cromwells. File includes sketches and a photograph. 1939–1943 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and related materials concerning purchase of a Persian tent, tiles, etc. from H. Kevorkian. 1941 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence relating to a variety of administrative activities at Shangri La. 1948–1954 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence relating to exchanges between Johnny Gomez in Hawaii and A.F. Brown (Aggie). Topics of discussions include payments to staff, corrections to accounting, and updates by Johnny Gomez concerning activities at Shangri La. Though the correspondence mainly refers to business at Shangri La, some notes refer to operations in Newport and the “Lair” in CA. Other correspondents present in the letters include, but are not limited to Louisa Jackson, Charlie Allcock, and S.L. Hawkins. 1948–1949, 1955–1963 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and other documents relating to a shipment of Egyptian tile via American Express to Honolulu. 1950–1951 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence to Doris Duke from Asfar & Sarkis, Damascus, Syria, regarding purchases, etc. (in French). *File may contain letters of sensitive/romantic nature. 1952–1960, 1974, 1982 (1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence to Doris Duke from Asfar & Sarkis, Damascus, Syria, regarding purchases, etc. (in French). *File may contain letters of sensitive/romantic nature. 1952–1960, 1974, 1982 (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence relating to the purchase of property lots Nos. 49, 50, and 53 by Doris Duke through Johnny Gomez, Edward Enos, and Marshall Henshaw. 1954–1956 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, to and from Wyeth & King, architects, regarding the shipment of drawings. 1959 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to general, administrative activities. 1964–1969 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and professional services rendered, statements relating to J. Harold Hughes’s work for Doris Duke in Hawaii. 1965 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to Doris Duke’s permission to pay selected Honolulu bills. Includes 2 bills. 1967–1968 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, notes, claim forms, and customs forms relating to the delivery and damage during delivery of a marble fireplace from The Gem Palace in India on its way to Shangri La. 1971–1977 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to a variety of subject matters including a burglary of the Playhouse (1974), purchase orders, solar heating, and other routine business matters. 1973–1984 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to daily administrative matters at Shangri La. Topics include claims to objects damaged in transport and other shipments to HI. 1976–1979 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to routine business matters like the shipment of packages, billing, quotes for projects, and related invoices pertaining to work performed at Shangri La including a new seawater intake pipe for Swimming Pool. 1976–1979 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Letter to Violet Mimaki from Liz at Duke Farms and catalog relating to inventory research. 1977 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Materials relating to Doris Duke’s purchase of turquoise and sapphire blue tiles through Serkan China, Marketing & Export. 1979–1981 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Directions to hang lanterns at Shangri La Playhouse. Includes photos. July 1986 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to Doris Duke’s purchase of mosaic tile panels for Shangri La. Object can be seen in enclosed Sotheby’s catalog, item No. 176. Purchased for $445,500. File includes related invoices and customs documents. 1992–1993 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Faxes, correspondence, and memoranda relating to Shangri La’s purchase of a new FAX machine. File also includes proposals for window repairs (Note these items were sent to Bernard Lafferty a few weeks after Doris Duke’s death. November 10, 1993). 1992–1993 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence with Linda Diller regarding door panels. May 23, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with the Pet Clinic in Honolulu, Hawaii regarding the care of Doris Duke’s dogs. 1991–1995 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - General correspondence from Shangri La to the DBO and Doris Duke. 1993 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - General correspondence to Shangri La from the DBO. Mainly includes clippings regarding the handling of the Estate of Doris Duke. 1994 (1 of 2) (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - General correspondence to Shangri La from the DBO. Mainly includes clippings regarding the handling of the Estate of Doris Duke. 1994 (2 of 2) (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - General correspondence to Shangri La from the DBO. Mainly includes clippings regarding the handling of the Estate of Doris Duke. 1995 (1 of 2) (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - General correspondence to Shangri La from the DBO. Mainly includes clippings regarding the handling of the Estate of Doris Duke. 1995 (2 of 2) (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - General memoranda to Shangri La from the DBO regarding established policies and procedures at Shangri La. 1996 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - General correspondence to Shangri La from the DBO. 1997 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence with Yolanda Crowe regarding her visiting Shangri La. Includes clippings regarding the making of a movie about Doris Duke. 1998–1999 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence between Shangri La and the DBO. Includes correspondence regarding shoreline disputes. Also includes clippings and correspondence regarding the death of Johnny Gomez. 1998–2000 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence between Drew Baker and James Cromwell and Doris Duke Cromwell regarding the construction of Shangri La, 1938 Sep-Oct (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Administrative Records, 1935-2003 and undated
  Topics in this series are widely varied, however they are all related to the Shangri La residence. Materials include inventories of shipments of furniture and other household items purchased by Doris Duke and her husband James Cromwell from locations such as Siam, Japan, China, India, and Europe, receipted bills and disbursements for "Honolulu", invoices, statements and vouchers relating to repairs at Shangri La (many with an "OK DD" signature), and detailed reports of expenditures for the construction and general upkeep of the residence. Also included in the series are legal documentation, including contracts, survey maps related to the purchase of the land and the construction of the home, and hundreds of recipes for a variety of meals that were presumably prepared at Shangri La (including Doris Duke's Bittersweet Chocolate Ice Milk and recipes from "Mrs. Castro"). Of particular interest are the inventories of items at Shangri La such as furnishings and decorative objects. These inventories typically include color photographs for each item as well as detailed information about when and where the item originated, when and where it was purchased, and its cost.
  - Purchases made in Siam, Japan, China, and India. 1935 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Receipted bills, accounts, bank statements, and cancelled checks relating to business activities at Shangri La. 1935–1936 (1 of 2) (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Receipted bills, accounts, bank statements, and cancelled checks relating to business activities at Shangri La. 1935–1936 (2 of 2) (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Bills of lading for shipping and storage from Thomas Cook & Son and others. 1935–1962 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Payment summaries and lists of goods shipped overseas to Shangri La. 1935–1940, 1980, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Invoices and statements relating to a variety of services rendered at Shangri La. Such services include architectural services, demolition of some blocks and wall, and wall covering. File also includes contract for purchase of 1981 Toyota Celica for Duke Farms by Violet Mimaki in HI. 1936, 1939, 1960–1969, 1980–1981 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Invoices and vouchers submitted by Wyeth & King, architects. 1937–1939 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Summaries of payments a/c purchase and improvement of Honolulu property. 1937–1939 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Invoices, statements, and vouchers relating to the repair of plumbing and drainage facilities at Shangri La. 1937–1939, 1951–1977 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Invoices, statements, and vouchers relating to Pool maintenance including the repair of broken pipes and the labor and materials to put diving board into operation. 1937, 1968–1982 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Invoices, statements, and vouchers relating to lighting and electrical work performed at Shangri La. 1937, 1939, 1941, 1961–1983 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Invoices, receipts, and related materials for invisible glass aquaria in Dining Room at Shangri La. File includes other window related adjustments. 1937–1938, 1968, 1982–1985 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Invoices and receipts for purchases. 1938 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Invoices for purchases made from A. Rabenou. 1938–1945 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Invoices, statements, and vouchers relating to the furnishing and installation of marble and tile at Shangri La. Several statements make reference to services rendered in the Turkish Room. 1938, 1961–1963, 1972, 1980–1982 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Purchases made for Shangri La. 1939 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Expenditure reports/expense statements. 1939–1947 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Invoices and copies of checks relating to Arden Cromwell’s burial and Miss Duke’s hospital bills. 1940 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Invoices pertaining to a variety of services including matting of a drawing, the repair of a liquor bowl, and the transport of a rug via United Airlines freight services. 1941, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Invoices, statements, vouchers, and work orders relating to roofing maintenance at the Main Residence and the Playhouse at Shangri La. 1955, 1962–1982 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Invoices, statements, and vouchers relating to masonry work performed at Shangri La. 1958, 1962–1964, 1971–1975, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Invoice from Hawaiian Bitumuls & Paving Co., Ltd. for paving of the Tennis Court with Laykold Mastic and paint lines at Shangri La. 1959 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Invoices, statements, and vouchers relating to the furnishing, installation, repair, and removal of flooring at Shangri La. 1960–1973 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Invoice for lamination of seven shade panels at Shangri La. July 29, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Invoices for upholstery work performed at Shangri La. 1964–1966, 1980–1981 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Invoices relating to the installation and repair of fences at Shangri La. 1964–1981 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Invoices and work orders for work performed at Shangri La. Work includes electrical fixture at Playhouse and treatments of Turkish Room. 1966, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Invoices, vouchers, and Contractor’s License for fiber glassing and waterproofing at Shangri La. 1966, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - House expenses for Shangri La. January 1967 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Statements of accounts for Doris Duke at the First National Bank of Hawaii. January 1967–December 1969 (Box 8, Folder 3)